Guide to the Ethical Culture Fieldston School Records 1879-2017 MS 3042
New-York Historical Society
- Record Group 3. Fieldston School (1925-2012; 18.75 linear feet), 216926; 18.75 Linear feet
  - Series I. Administrative affairs, 1927-2012; 216927; 13.25 Linear feet
    - Subseries I.A. Senior administration, 1927-1993; 217082
      - Senior administration subject files (38 folders), 1967-1993; 233214 (Offsite-box 69, Folder 1-38)
        From the administrations of principals Spencer Brown, Kenneth Barton, and Ellen Stern, as well as administrator David Schwartz. Files: Academic honesty, Administration, Administrative structure, Business office, Calendars, Cheating, Comparative Study [of revenue], Dewitt-Wallace Reader's Digest Fund, Diversity, Drug education, Education Records Bureau testing (2 folders), Faculty memos, Form lists, High school mailings, History department, Independent Schools Opportunity Project, Lunch, Middle school, Minority experiences at Fieldston, New York State Pupil Evaluation, Nemerov dinner, Albert G. Oliver program, Open School Evening, Planning Committee, Professional development, Questionnaire - midwinter vacation, Report on morale, Science Department, Student discipline, Student leadership conference, Study halls (Black and Latin-American Students Club), Sit-in, Suspensions, Trips.
      - Kenneth Barton papers, 1972-1985; 233215 (Offsite-box 69, Box 39)
        Correspondence.
      - Ellen Stern papers, 1973-1990; 233216 (Offsite-box 69, Folder 40)
      - David Shapiro papers, 1991 (Offsite-box 69, Folder 41)
        Correspondence, primarily letters to parents.
      - Administrative Detail Committee (4 folders), 1961-1971; 233217 (Offsite-box 69, Folder 42-45)
        Notes and meeting minutes, discussing specific school policies and their enforcement.
      - Fieldston Executive Committee (11 folders), 1934-1969, 1973 (Offsite-box 70, Folder 1-11)
        Meeting minutes, with a small amount of correspondence. Topics include curriculum and academic programs, college preparation, athletics and extracurricular activities, community work, faculty, administrative structure, events, and discipline. Matters discussed broadly, with very few mentions of specific staff members or students. 1973 letter with Faculty Council by-laws. No records for 1935 or 1951.
      - Report of the Visiting Committee, 1951 (9 folders), 1950-1952 (Offsite-box 70, Folder 18-26)
        Reports, correspondence, evaluation criteria, background materials, and preparatory materials (forms filled out by staff members). Visiting Committee made up of representatives from other independent schools.
    - Subseries I.B. School evaluation and studies, 1932-1980; 217084
      This subseries includes records for studies of the Fieldston School, mostly by external organizations. The bulk of the subseries is made up of records from the Eight-Year Study, including extensive correspondence of Principal Herbert W. Smith.
      This subseries is arranged in chronological order.
      - "A Student Report to the School", 1943; 217085 (Offsite-box 70, Folder 12)
      - Commission on Secondary Schools report, 1942 (5 folders), 1941-1947 (Offsite-box 70, Folder 13-17)
        1942 report from Commission, with progress reports to the Commission in 1945 and 1947. Correspondence and memoranda, and questionnaires filled out by staff members (mostly on their schedules).
      - Report of the Visiting Committee, 1951 (9 folders), 1950-1952 (Offsite-box 70, Folder 18-26)
      - Education Problems at Fieldston: A Pilot Study, 1952, 1952-1959 (Offsite-box 70, Folder 27)
        Report from the Research Center for Human Relations, New York University.
      - Commission on Secondary Schools report, 1960 (8 folders), 1960-1961 (Offsite-box 71, Folder 1-8)
        Includs report, evaluative criteria, committee materials, and supplementary materials on Fieldston's philosophy and faculty.
      - Evaluation Report, 1971, 1969-1971 (Offsite-box 71, Folder 9)
        Report from the Evaluation Committee, with related correspondence.
      - Evaluation Report, 1975 (Offsite-box 71, Folder 10)
        Report from the Evaluation Committee, two copies.
      - Eight Year Study - early proposals (2 folders), 1932-1933 (Offsite-box 71, Folder 11-12)
      - Eight Year Study - college admissions and evaluations of college students (7 folders), 1934-1938 (Offsite-box 71, Folder 13-19)
        Correspondence and questionnaires.
      - Eight Year study - published materials (6 folders), 1934-1941, 1980 (Offsite-box 71, Folder 20-25)
        Brochures, news clippings, and academic publications from the Progressive Education Association and others. Includes Report of the Committee on Experimental Schools, 1937.
      - Eight Year Study - Herbert W. Smith papers (4 folders), 1933-1937 (Offsite-box 71, Folder 26-29)
        Correspondence, with some notes and meeting materials. Correspondence primarily with other administrators, those from the Progressive Education Association, and others from ECFS.
      - Eight Year Study - Herbert W. Smith papers (6 folders), 1933-1938 (Offsite-box 72, Folder 1-6)
      - Eight Year Study - supplementary materials (28 folders), 1934-1938 (Offsite-box 72, Folder 7-34)
        Evaluations, background materials, meeting minutes, correspondence, drafts, reports.
      - Eight Year Study - reports from Fieldston to the Commission (5 folders), 1934-1940 (Offsite-box 72, Folder 35-39)
      - Eight Year Study - reports from other schools to the Commission (8 folders), 1935-1939 (Offsite-box 73, Folder 1-8)
      - Eight Year Study - additional materials, 1935-1937 (Offsite-box 318, Folder 14)
        Two reports from Principal Herbert W. Smith to the Commission on the Relation of Secondary School and College, along with supplementary materials on curriculum for English, Latin, art and "verbal expression," and copy of Annual Report to Board of Governors, 1837. (Possibly duplicate copies of materials found in Box 70 through 73.)
    - Subseries I.C. Faculty, 1928-2000; 217087
      This subseries is made up of records related to policies, work, and concerns of Fieldston School faculty.
      This subseries is arranged in chronological order, followed by faculty schedules and miscellaneous items.
      - Fieldston Teachers' Council (4 folders), 1932-1950 (Offsite-box 73, Folder 9-12)
        Records of the faculty liaison group to the Board of Governors. Includes minutes and meeting notes and correspondence on topics including salaries, schedules, and educational policy.
      - Faculty meetings (10 folders), 1937-1971 (Offsite-box 73, Folder 13-22)
        Meeting notes and minutes on topics including disciplinary policies, curriculum, committee work, new hires, event planning, facilities, and schedules.
      - Faculty policies (4 folders), 1972-1995 (Offsite-box 73, Folder 23-26)
        Includes meeting materials, correspondence, handbooks, and examination materials.
      - Faculty advisors, 1990-2000, undated (Offsite-box 73, Folder 27)
      - Faculty schedules (8 folders), 1928-1932 (Offsite-box 73, Folder 28-37)
        Weekly class schedules.
      - Faculty - miscellaneous, 1957, 1974-1999 (Offsite-box 73, Folder 38)
        Primarily all-faculty correspondence and lists of new teachers.
    - Subseries I.D. Fieldston Upper matters, 1928-2012; 233021
      This subseries includes records on various topics affecting Fieldston students, staff, and parents.
      This subseries is arranged in alphabetical order.
      - Commencement (4 folders), 1936-1992; 217089 (Offsite-box 74, Folder 1-4)
        Valedictory addresses, planning correspondence, graduation dinner materials, and diploma design examples.
      - Commencement - programs and invitations (4 folders), 1929-2000 (Offsite-box 74, Folder 5-8)
        Incomplete run.
      - Commencement ephemera (2 folders), 1938-2010 (Offsite-box 64, Folder 1-2)
      - Diploma examples, 1935-1960 (Offsite-box 272, Folder 2)
      - Fieldston Bulletin (5 folders), 1942-1956, 1991-1998; 217094 (Offsite-box 74, Folder 9-13)
        Daily notices for faculty and administration, for 1942, 1948, 1956, 1991-1994, 1996-1998.
      - Fieldston Bulletin (7 folders), 1980, 1992-2012 (Offsite-box 64, Folder 3-9)
      - Fieldston plans, undated (Offsite-box 74, Folder 14)
      - Guidance department (8 folders), 1934-1980 (Offsite-box 74, Folder 15-22)
        Correspondence, memorandum, meeting minutes, mostly on college application and selection.
      - Health Forms, 1930; 217095 (Offsite-box 74, Folder 23)
        Brief forms on history of illnesses and immunizations.
      - Health policies, 1987, 1997 (Offsite-box 74, Folder 24)
        Includes AIDS policy.
      - Mailings to Parents, 1963-2000, undated; 217460 (Offsite-box 74, Folder 25)
      - News clippings, 1961-1990 (Offsite-box 74, Folder 26)
      - Parent guidelines committee, 1977-1988 (Offsite-box 74, Folder 27)
        Includes discussion of non-school sponsored parties.
      - Publicity programs, 1954-1961 (Offsite-box 74, Folder 28)
      - Special events and ceremonies (2 folders), 1953-1992; 217092 (Offsite-box 74, Folder 29-30)
        Includes 1980 dedication of Fieldston auditorium.
      - Tate Library and reading lists (3 folders), 1930-1936, 1978-1993; 217093 (Offsite-box 74, Folder 31-33)
        Includes 1936 Parent & Teacher accession book.
      - Tate Library - accession books (6 folders), 1969-1992 (Offsite-box 75, Folder 1-6)
      - Tate Library - accession ledgers, 1928-1944, 1951-1986, 1993-1995 (Offsite-box 63)
        Accession ledgers listing book purchases for the library at Fieldston.
      - Tate Library - acquisition lists, 1948, 1997-1999 (Offsite-box 64, Folder 10)
        New book lists. Also 1948 list of "periodicals received at the Fieldston School."
      - Tate Library - accounts and budgets, 1967-1981 (Offsite-box 64, Folder 11)
      - Tate Library - circulation records, 1977-1993 (Offsite-box 64, Folder 12)
        Monthly reports, with some daily records from 1992.
      - Tate Library donors, circa 1970 (Offsite-box 63)
        Book with list of names of donors for the construction of Tate Library.
  - Series II. Academic affairs, 1925-2012; 216928; 4 Linear feet
    Series II concerns academics at Fieldston, with examples of curriculum material and student work making up the bulk of the series. The series also contains some materials related to home grade reports, and examples of departmental business (such as correspondence and budgets).
    Subseries II.A. Departments and curriculum
    Subseries II.B. Student work
    - Subseries II.A. Departments and curriculum, 1925-2012; 217097
      Subseries II.A includes information on home grade reports, departmental business, and curriculum. The volume and date range of materials available varies greatly between departments.
      This subseries begins with information regarding home grade reports, followed by academic department reports in chronological order. The remaining files are in alphabetical order.
      - Home reports, 1934-1939, 1942-1946 (Offsite-box 75, Folder 7)
        Home reports for students Hilda Lazarus Pearlman and Sanford Ehrmann. Includes 1991 and 1998 letters granting permission for use in archive.
      - Home reports - procedures (2 folders), 1941, 1975-1983 (Offsite-box 75, Folder 8-9)
        Sample home reports on student progress, along with correspondence and instructions for grading and creating reports.
      - Department reports (18 folders), 1935-1964 (Offsite-box 75, Folder 10-28)
        End of year reports from the following departments: Art, Economics, English, Ethics, Household Arts, History, Latin, French and Spanish, German, Graphic Art, Mathematics, Mechanic Arts, Music, Printing, Psychology, Science, and Speech and Drama. Also includes some reports on the School and Community Committee, Middle School, field trips, festivals, and the library. Number and type of reports varies each year.
      - Department reports (7 folders), 1964-1971, 1987-1989 (Offsite-box 76, Folder 1-7)
        Additional end of year departmental reports.
      - Inter-department business (5 folders), 1937-1942 (Offsite-box 76, Folder 8-12)
        Relating to budgets, committees, student council, rules, and teaching apprentices.
      - Alternative learning period, 1974-2000 (Offsite-box 76, Folder 13)
      - Art, 1939-1945, 1962-1979 (Offsite-box 76, Folder 14)
      - Biology, 1965-1967 (Offsite-box 76, Folder 15)
      - Book order forms - all departments, 1975-1983 (Offsite-box 76, Folder 16)
      - Business, 1925-1931 (Offsite-box 76, Folder 17)
      - Ceramics, 1938, 1993 (Offsite-box 76, Folder 18)
      - Cinema (2 folders), 1970 (Offsite-box 76, Folder 19-20)
      - Computers, 1982-1990 (Offsite-box 76, Folder 21)
      - Curriculum Committee, 1972-1974, 1981-1983 (Offsite-box 76, Folder 22)
      - English (11 folders), 1932-1997 (Offsite-box 76, Folder 23-33)
        Includes "The Arts in Modern Society" by Elbert Lenrow, Research Associate and Teacher of English," 1936. Also includes African-American literature and Southern literature curriculum materials from the 1980s-1990s.
      - English, 1936 (Offsite-box 64, Folder 13)
        Duplicate copy of ""The Arts in Modern Society" by Elbert Lenrow.
      - Ethics (2 folders), 1931-1962 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 1-2)
        See Record Group 13 for additional material on Ethics programs.
      - Fieldston plan, 1933-1934 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 3)
      - Forms I and II, undated (Offsite-box 77, Folder 4)
      - Graphic arts and printing (2 folders), 1938-1991 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 5-6)
      - History (4 folders), 1948-2000 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 7-10)
        Includes information on 1972 trip to Greece and 1991 trip to Italy.
      - History - United States (5 folders), 1998-2000 (Offsite-box 79, Folder 14-18)
        Includes the "Fieldston American Reader" and Form IV resource and reader notebooks.
      - Homework, 1955 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 11)
        Questionnaires on homework load.
      - Languages, 1976, 1984 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 12)
      - Math (2 folders), 1936, 1975-1987 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 13-14)
        Includes "Introducing Geometry" by Joseph Jablonower, 1936.
      - Math (2 folders), 1962, undated (Offsite-box 79, Folder 19-20)
        Includes texts on pre-calculus and geometry written by faculty.
      - Mechanic arts, 1933-1943 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 15)
      - Music - jazz, circa 1950s (Offsite-box 64, Folder 14)
        Notes and lecture schedule for History of American Jazz course.
      - Music - jazz (9 folders), 1996-2012 (Offsite-box 295, Folder 1-9)
        Papers of Tom Christenson. Primarily evaluations and score sheets (with some cassettes) from student competitions at the Berklee High School Jazz Festival. Also includes notes from students, photographs, and ephemera used in teaching.
      - Music and dance, 1984 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 16)
      - Physical education, 1976-1982, undated (Offsite-box 77, Folder 17)
      - Pre-calculus, undated (Offsite-box 79, Folder 14)
        Student copy of textbook "Pre-Calculus Mathematics," circa mid-20th century.
      - Psychology, 1984-1986 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 18)
      - Science (2 folders), 1960-1988 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 19-20)
      - Science, 1971-1998 (Offsite-box 79, Folder 21)
      - Senior projects (2 folders), 1963-1968 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 21-22)
        Includes records of the Senior End of Year Committee, 1963-1967.
      - Sex education, 1983 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 23)
      - Social studies, 1970-1982 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 24)
      - Special programs, 1979-1982 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 25)
        Bilingual exchange programs, mini-week.
      - Summaries of program and schedules, 1977-1982, 1991 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 26)
        Schedules and lists of course offerings.
      - Urban arts, circa 1980s (Offsite-box 77, Folder 27)
        Photographs.
      - Wood arts, 1933 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 28)
      - Miscellaneous curriculum, 1931-1992, undated (Offsite-box 77, Folder 29)
        Includes 1931 report on activities of each department and 1951 brochure on curriculum.
      - Miscellaneous curriculum, 1969-1978, 1983 (Offsite-box 64, Folder 15)
        Memorandum, correspondence, course descriptions.
    - Subseries II.B. Student work, 1931-2005; 217098
      Subseries II.B is made up of examples of student class work, as well as some photographs and ephemera from student field trips and events.
      - Science festival play script, after 1917 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 30)
      - Joan of Arc, 1936 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 31)
        Bound copy of script with description of student production.
      - Form I class journal and yearbook, 1934, 1937 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 32)
        Both include photographs.
      - Student work, circa 1930s (Offsite-box 77, Folder 33)
      - Print shop, 1939, 1981 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 34)
      - Senior English seminars, 1945-1970 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 35)
      - Chemistry notebook, 1949 (Offsite-box 64, Folder 16)
      - Class trip to Allied Textile Printers (2 folders), 1954 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 36-37)
        Photographs and captions adhered to construction paper, bound with string. Includes student essays describing trip to Allied Textile Printers, a textile manufacturer, in Paterson, New Jersey in March of 1954.
      - Class trip to A.J. Siris Products, circa 1954 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 38)
        Construction paper with captions and photographs adhered. Tour of A.J. Siris Products Corporation, referred to as a "powder puff packing plant."
      - Class trip to Scalamandre plant, 1956 (Offsite-box 64, Folder 17)
      - Class trips, 1950s (Offsite-box 77, Folder 39)
        Photographs of field trips, including ice-skating. Other photographs possibly additional Allied Textile Printers or A.J. Siris Products field trip images.
      - Student exhibits, fairs, and festivals, 1957-2001 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 40)
      - Music work, 1964 (Offsite-box 78, Folder 1)
      - Mathematics and science work, 1979-1988 (Offsite-box 78, Folder 2)
      - Ethics essays, 1931-1982 (Offsite-box 78, Folder 3)
      - Independent study and senior projects, 1964-1977 (Offsite-box 78, Folder 4)
      - Languages - French and Spanish, 1986, 1997 (Offsite-box 78, Folder 5)
      - English and History essays, 1987-2000 (Offsite-box 78, Folder 6)
      - Forms II and IV - French, 1996-1997 (Offsite-box 78, Folder 7)
      - French (illustrated story), 1997 (Offsite-box 64, Folder 18)
      - Miscellaneous student work, 1972-2005 (Offsite-box 78, Folder 8)
        Script for "The Graduwits or Waiting for Goto," 1972. Photocopy of illustrated description of water cycle and class trip to reservoir, 1990.
  - Series III. Student life, 1929-2001; 216929; 1.5 Linear feet
    This series contains records on extracurricular student activities, including clubs, athletics, the arts, performances, student government, and events. Materials on school rules and regulations are also included.
    This series is arranged in alphabetical order.
    - Assemblies, 1944-1998; 217107 (Offsite-box 78, Folder 9)
      Includes 1994 Multicultural Assembly program signed by David Dinkins.
    - Athletics (5 folders), 1955-2001; 217101 (Offsite-box 78, Folder 10-14)
      Ephemera, schedules, track and swim records, photographs, correspondence. Correspondence and ephemera related to the Metropolitan Athletic Association of Private Schools. Includes some records created by or related to Alton Smith.
    - Athletics clippings book, 1932-1934 (Offsite-box 62, Folder 4)
    - Awareness Day, 1990, 1998; 217108 (Offsite-box 78, Folder 15)
    - Community and work service, 1965-1997; 217109 (Offsite-box 78, Folder 16)
    - Conference on Energy, 1980 (Offsite-box 78, Folder 17)
    - Dance performances (3 folders), 1951-1998 (Offsite-box 78, Folder 18-20)
    - Drama performances (4 folders), 1929-2000 (Offsite-box 78, Folder 21-24)
      Includes senior plays and musicals.
    - Environmental club, 1990 (Offsite-box 78, Folder 25)
    - Festivals (2 folders), 1935-1968 (Offsite-box 78, Folder 26-27)
      Includes 1945 Freedom Festival.
    - Fieldston Enrichment Program, 1987-1998 (Offsite-box 78, Folder 28)
    - Fieldston Radio Club, 1935 (Offsite-box 78, Folder 29)
      Handbook and student publication.
    - Junior Peace Council, 1934 (Offsite-box 78, Folder 30)
    - Miscellaneous events, 1974-1998 (Offsite-box 78, Folder 31)
    - Mothers, Fathers, and Parents Days, 1960-1967; 217106 (Offsite-box 79, Folder 1)
    - Music performances (4 folders), 1966-2001 (Offsite-box 79, Folder 2-5)
    - Rules and regulations (4 folders), 1961-1985; 217100 (Offsite-box 79, Folder 6)
      General school rules, along with policies and rules for dress codes, theater and library spaces, dining room, study hall, drug use, and graduation.
    - Schools-on-the-Hill Music Festival, 1938; 217105 (Offsite-box 79, Folder 7)
    - Student government, 1943-1959, 1972-1998; 217102 (Offsite-box 79, Folder 8-10)
      By-laws and constitutions. Meeting minutes and ephemera. Group also known as Student Council and PAC.
    - Student organizations, 1945-1995; 217103 (Offsite-box 79, Folder 11)
    - Student publications, 1967, 1977, undated; 217104 (Offsite-box 79, Folder 12-13)
    - Schools-on-the-Hill Music Festival, 1938 (Offsite-box 79, Folder 7)
    - Urban Arts Day, 1992; 217110 (Offsite-box 79, Folder 14)
- Record Group 4. Midtown Ethical Culture School (1929-2008; 7 linear feet), 216931; 7 Linear feet
  This record group contains materials related to the Ethical Culture School in Midtown. Topics covered include school administration and curriculum, and common types of materials include ephemera, correspondence, reports, and student work. Student levels range from kindergarten to grades five or six (depending on the era), with a very small amount of pre-school materials.
  This record group only contains materials created after the opening of the Fieldston School campus in 1928; Ethical Culture School records created prior to 1928 can be found in Record Group 2. Additional related materials can be found in Record Group 1 and Record Group 11.
  This record group is organized into two series:
  Series II. Academic affairs and student life
  - Series I. Administrative affairs, 1939-1998; 216932; 1 Linear feet
    This series primarily contains records of principals and faculty at the Midtown school, along with some records for administrative committee and staff. Frequent topics include teaching methods, faculty matters, transportation and building issues, discipline, child psychology, and curriculum.
    Within this series, files of the administration are arranged in chronological order, followed by faculty files, also arranged in chronological order.
    - Principal Emily Henry, 1954; 217113 (Offsite-box 80, Folder 1)
      Text of talk given on "reading readiness."
    - Principal Allan Shedlin (3 folders), 1979-1983; 217114 (Offsite-box 80, Folder 2-4)
      Correspondence with parents, administrators at other schools, donors, and faculty. Includes "State of the School Report, 1975-1983."
    - Principal Jane Llewellyn (Southern), 1988-1991; 217115 (Offsite-box 80, Folder 5)
      Mostly memoranda to faculty. Includes 1988 report of the New York State Association for Independent Schools on the Midtown School.
    - Principal Joyce Baron, 1994 (Offsite-box 80, Folder 6)
      Letter from Director Jeanne Amster on Baron's appointment.
    - Committees (2 folders), 1940-1987 (Offsite-box 80, Folder 7-8)
      Executive Committee minutes (1940-1941), Midtown Principal Search Committee records (1982-1983), list of committee members (1987).
    - Mailings to parents, 1973-1991 (Offsite-box 80, Folder 9)